Finding Aid for Franklin H. Bailey papers, 1861-1912 [microform]
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Franklin H. Bailey papers [microform] 1861-1912
Bailey, Franklin H., 1845-1914.
2 microfilm reels
85694 mf 284c-285c
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was the gift of Mrs. J.R. Inman (donor no. 1207 ).
No further additions to the papers are expected.
The collection is open to research; for reasons of preservation; no access to the originals is allowed.
Originals of this collection are also available at the Bentley Historical Library.
Franklin H. Bailey was a soldier from Adrian, Michigan who served in Co. C, 4th Michigan Cavalry during the Civil War. He later was an astronomer, lecturer, and teacher at Hillsdale College. He then moved to Boston, Massachusetts where he invented what was a forerunner of the planetarium.
The Franklin H. Bailey collection consists of Civil War letters written to his parents in Adrian, Michigan concerning family affairs and army life. There are also letters he wrote to his wife Minerva while on a trip abroad in 1873. Other materials include a scrapbook of letters, 1880-1901, primarily concerning educational matters; enlistment and discharge certificates; diaries, 1865-1883, detailing his war service, student life at Hillsdale College, and his teaching and scientific interests. There is one Civil War letter, undated, of Minerva Bailey's first husband, Levi Greenfield, who served in Co. C, 18th Michigan Infantry.
Subjects:
Bailey, Franklin H., 1845-1914.; Adrian (Mich.); Astronomy.; Hillsdale College.; Inventions.; Shiloh, Battle of, Tenn., 1862.; United States. Army. Michigan Cavalry Regiment, 4th (1862-1865). Company C.; United States. Army. Michigan Infantry Regiment, 18th (1862-1865). Company C.; United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Bailey, Franklin H., 1845-1914.; Planetaria.
Contributors:
Greenfield, Levi, 1836-1865.
Genre Terms:
Diaries.; Photographs.; Scrapbooks.
- Civil War and later materials
  - Biographical information (Reel 1)
  - Correspondence
    - November-December 1861 (Reel 1)
    - January-February 1862 (Reel 1)
    - March-April 1862 (Reel 1)
    - September-December 1863 (Reel 1)
    - January-March 1864 (Reel 1)
    - April-June 1864 (Reel 1)
    - August-October 1864 (Reel 1)
    - November-December 1864 (Reel 1)
    - January-June 1865 (Reel 1)
    - July-August 1865 (Reel 1)
    - April-July 1865 (official communications) (Reel 1)
    - Undated letter from Levi Greenfield to wife, Minerva, who later married F. H. Bailey (Reel 1)
    - May-July 1873, July 1879 letters from abroad to wife, Minerva (Reel 1)
    - 1880-1901 (Reel 1)
  - Poem about the Civil War (Reel 1)
  - Certificates: enlistment and discharge papers (Reel 1)
  - Miscellanea: Civil War songbook and two soldiers' hymnbooks (Reel 1)
  - Receipts for courses at Hillsdale College, 1871-1873 (Reel 1)
  - Diaries
    - 1865-1870 (Reel 1)
    - 1871-1880 (Reel 2)
    - 1882-1883 (Reel 2)
  - Miscellanea regarding invention, Bailey's Astral Lantern (Reel 2)
  - Scrapbook (Reel 2)
  - Photographs
    - F.H. Bailey (Reel 2)
    - Grace Bailey Inman (his daughter) with her father's school-size cosmosphere (Reel 2)